[Music]
okay friends remember you did this to
yourself we're gonna talk in blistering
speed about metabolism for performance I
know most of you we're gonna miss a lot
of this but I don't care I'm gonna try
to ram this out in five minutes or less
in fact I got a lot less because I'm
wasting time right now if you want to
learn more about this you're gonna have
to check out the other videos
particularly the long physiology of
fatigue or endurance and I have some
extensive videos on it so now that we're
down to like four minutes here we go
okay when you ingest food it starts in
your mouth let's assume we're talking
about carbohydrate to start okay when
that goes in your stomach
by the time it leaves your stomach it's
no longer a carbohydrate it is now in
the form typically of glucose which is a
six carbon molecule when it leaves your
stomach it's gonna then enter your blood
also in the form of glucose now you will
take glucose and you will store it in
one of three places either in the liver
as muscle glycogen in the muscle as
muscle glycogen or a little bit of it
depending on what is going on will be
stored as adipose tissue now this
process called de novo lipogenesis is
not excessive so that air was a little
bit small but this depends on a lot of
different things other videos okay now
if you take fat and you ingest that say
this wonderful piece of cheese well
that's gonna leave your stomach in the
form of a free fatty acid so it's
smaller components it's gonna then enter
your blood but before that depending on
kind of what you do here there is a
little bit in how your stomach converts
fatty acids and glucose back and forth
Google resistant starches do you want to
know more about that particularly how
you can try to make a fiber actually
into a shorter chain fatty acid but
nonetheless mostly fatty acids will go
into the blood that is fatty acid you'll
store those in a handful places you can
convert some fatty acids into glycogen
called the gluconeogenesis formation of
new glucose from non glucose molecules
but you can store it also in the muscle
as I Mt
so this would be an intramuscular
triglyceride this is a positive thing
and we can use this for a nurse
performance or you can store it as a
triglyceride in adipose tissue now in
terms of protein that's getting your
stomach be digested and it's gonna be
moved on as its individual amino acid
components depending on what type of
protein you get therefore it's in the
blood it is an amino acid in terms of
storage again you can store a little bit
of excess amino acid as a triglyceride
but not not much often you're most
likely gonna excrete it if it's waste
you can store some of it a small amount
of amino acids in muscle which is good
because then you can use those amino
acids to generate things like muscle
cells immune cells antibodies no
transmitters hormones insulin who knows
who knows what else you can do it then
okay and then again some of that can be
converted in through gluconeogenesis as
well but again we're talking at a fairly
small no I'm a little bit behind time so
I got to speed up a little bit here we
go yeah we've got our stored energy
system so we're gonna have to in order
to get stored energy into the exercising
mouth so we got to put it back in the
blood and move it to whatever muscle is
being exercised but let's start actually
up the muscle now when you exercise
depending what you're doing you're
primarily going to use the fuel that is
in the exercising muscle obviously this
makes most sense it's right there it's
going to be faster if I start taking
fuel from another organ tissue it got a
pick in blood move through the buddy
that's just gonna be a lot slower so the
first thing I'm gonna use is is
carbohydrate that stored muscle glycogen
we talked about we're gonna int a belies
that through a Plaza process called
glycolysis lysis meaning to split glyco
meaning like again so glycolysis is a
splitting of glycogen what happens there
is we take those six carbon molecules we
split it up into two separate 3 carbon
molecules we call those things pyruvate
now as a result of that we get a couple
little stars two to three now those
stars are what are called ATV that's the
energy currency of all cells in other
words that the only way anything about
you can actually make usable energy but
we only get to three it's a very very
small amount if we have sufficient
oxygen available in the tissue we can
take that pyruvate and ship it up in
this other blue little circle we call
the mitochondria any time you hear the
word aerobic or oxidative
you automatically know this is going
down in the mitochondria you notice that
I call us this half
in the cytoplasm Ursinus all outside of
the mitochondria it's anaerobic once we
want a lot of fully metabolize that
carbohydrate molecule we have to
actually take it through a role of
catabolism which means we have to ship
it to the mitochondria so we take those
two separate three carbon molecules we
then break them down individually into a
separate two carbon molecules called
acid Ocoee now that we went from three
carbons 6 to 3 to 2 which means we lost
one carbon with each one of those
conversions we're gonna take those
additional carbons bound those to those
oxygens make carbon dioxide and go and
breathe that out check out the five the
all my videos on physiology fat loss you
wanna learn more about that how about
carbon dioxide Oh to think that lossing
works
nonetheless we take that a Satoko weight
and then that conversion we make a cup a
little more star it's not a big deal
we're gonna take that through another
little circular process called tri
silicic acid cycle or often known as
Krebs cycle in most expose circles gives
you a little bit of ATP couple more co2
back to co2 each and we went from six to
three two two two two two zero zero Wow
now as a result of that try so a gas
would we cycle we make a whole bunch of
high-energy metabolites or substrates
that we can use our hydrogen or medius
excuse me and it's real to that we get a
bunch more ATP and that's really how we
can generate a lot of ATP well so the
reason why carbohydrates can be used for
both anaerobic and aerobic right because
you have to be started anaerobically
finished row buckley to be fully
metabolize in terms of amino acid that
arrows small you can use it senate it's
a hundred percent oxidative so there's
no anaerobic metabolism going on there
if you want to use your fuels got to be
oxidative got a ship to the mitochondria
it's got two carbons so it's gonna
process similar to acetic away it's
gonna run through Krebs cycle
yadda yadda I'm gonna get more of those
stars in terms of using fat the first
thing you're gonna have to do is
separate that I MTG into a whole bunch
of different categories so you have the
three red ones there in the middle and
those three carbon molecules are called
glycerol so it's a three carbon backbone
those other big chains are there fatty
acid chains and and the length of the
fatty acid chains is 12 to 20 ish
depending upon to energy and carbon
carbohydrate first thing we have to do
then is ship those glycerols into the
in the mitochondrion it runs and forms
just like pyruvate did why because it's
three carbon molecule more ATP more
Krebs cycle it cetera in terms of those
fatty acids though we have to ship them
through a little transporter called
carnitine alright that's actually the
rate limiting step to using oxygen or
using fat as a fuel
yeah it's limited by lipolysis our sorry
oxidation not my pulses and oxidation is
limited by carnitine not carnosine not
creatine okay make sure you don't makes
it make up the difference a you have
these big long then chains of fatty acid
what you're going to do for those is
cleave off or cut two carbons at a time
it's in the mitochondria so it's
oxidation you're cutting one two at a
time so we call this process ready ready
ready beta oxidation ah yes so sort it
is since you cut two off at a time you
can handle it and process it kind of
just like you do acidotic away run
through krebs cycle bunch of our ATP
every time you cut cut cut cut cut you
get two more carbon molecules run or
more and you get a whole bunch of ATP
because of that and this is why per
molecule per mole a single molecule of
fat is gonna give you much more energy
ATP then one molecule of carbohydrate
however it's actually technically less
efficient because the stoichiometry it's
not one-to-one in other words you need
one oxygen molecule to get one carbon of
carbohydrate gone you need less than
that or a little bit more than that for
fat and so it actually is a little bit
less metabolically efficient in terms of
per molecule of oxygen although you get
more total ATP so what that means is
we've got pros and cons carbohydrate is
not better or worse an or fat it's
better or worse for metabolism for
exercise they both have their pros and
the cons if it's a speed issue
carbohydrate if the downside of
carbohydrate though is you got limited
supply the benefit of fat unlimited
supply downside is it's too slow and
it's not as efficient right because we
only have a little bit of a MTG in the
exercising muscle so we have to go start
going outside of the exercising muscles
self to get our fat carbohydrate however
is most gonna be coming from the muscle
glycogen once muscle glycogen starts
running low we can start pulling glucose
from the blood that's great has to enter
through the cell through a glute for
transporter just like carnitine
the transporter that gets glucose into
the cell now you run through glycolysis
no problem once blood glucose starts
getting low and we start taking glycogen
from the liver on the issue there is
what happens when the liver runs out mmm
problem because I mentioned earlier if
blood glucose gets too low brain goes
yeah you go down hard to exercise like
that and terms are fat though we have a
whole unlimited supply basically of
adipose tissue we have a bunch of
triglycerides so the amount of lipolysis
we can do is basically unlimited we
break that stuff down we attach it to
albumin it has to be transported that
way through the blood we have to get it
into the muscle itself through a fatty
acid mining protein that baby baby right
in those in the form of a long-chain
fatty acid once we get into this tissue
then we have to transport it into the
model corner of your carnitine and you
see how we just have all these
additional extra steps now one little
note to add there one of the benefits of
medium or short train short chain fatty
acids is they have to go through fatty
acid binding protein but they don't have
to go through carnitine and this is why
these things are very popular for
nootropic effects energy effects and
other things is because they can slide
in the mitochondria and be used much
easier for a few now in other videos
I'll explain you then what the metabolic
rate limiting step for different types
of exercise are but hopefully that gave
you a quick primer and a teaser but back
next time when I got a little more
thanks a lot hope you enjoyed
[Music]